Lothar Wolff collection, 1926-1987
George Eastman Museum
Lothar Wolff collection,
1926-1987
25.4 cubic feet
George Eastman Museum
George Eastman Museum Moving Image Department George Eastman Museum 900 East Avenue Rochester, NY 14607 Phone: 585-271-3361 Fax: 585-256-3397 Email: stills@eastman.org URL: www.eastman.org
The Lothar Wolff Collection consists of correspondence (both business and personal), photographs, publications and clippings, research materials, awards and citations, artwork, and film and video dating from 1926 to 1987. The bulk of the collection represents Wolff’s professional career, including materials related to completed and proposed film and television projects and other business dealings; very little is of a personal nature. The collection includes material documenting Wolff’s involvement with many notable figures involved in motion pictures, including Louis de Rochemont, Louise Brooks, G. W. Pabst, and Paul Fejos.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open to research upon request.
Acquisition Information
TK
Custodial History
Materials were created and collected by Mr. Wolff during his lifetime (1909-1988). Following his death these materials were donated to the George Eastman Museum by his widow Violet M. Wolff.
Funding for this finding aid was provided by a grant from the Council on Library and Information Resources’ Hidden Collections Program.
Biographical Note
Lothar Wolff was born in Bromberg, Germany (later Bydgoszcz, Poland), on May 13, 1909, one of nine children, eight boys and one girl. Wolff's father was a furniture manufacturer and dealer; his mother was named Betty. In 1919 the Wolff family relocated to Charlottenburg, a locality of Berlin, where Wolff's father owned and operated a large three-story furniture warehouse and emporium, the top floor of which served as the family's residence. Soon after his father's death from cancer one year later, Wolff, his mother and sister traveled to Davos, Switzerland, where they sought treatment for his sister's tuberculosis. After a year abroad they returned to Germany where Wolff's sister soon died of her illness.
Though by his own account an indifferent student, Wolff nevertheless finished school with plans to follow in his older brother's footsteps and become an interior designer. In 1926 these plans changed when Wolff was introduced to one of his brother's clients,Samuel Rachman. Rachman, an American film impresario and former Paramount executive, had become head of UFA's distribution network (1). Rachman was instrumental in the formation of Parufamet, a Berlin-based German-American distribution company jointly formed by Paramount, UFA and Metro-Goldwyn-Meyer in late December, 1925. On September 29, 1926, Wolff joined Parufamet's publicity department and within a year was promoted from apprentice to publicity department head. From January through March 1927 Wolff also studied typing ("machine writing") at Rackow’s Kaufmännischen Privatschule (Commercial Private School). Wolff left Parufamet on November 1, 1927, but continued to work as an independent publicist. Among Wolff's most notable clients was German director G.W. Pabst, to whom Wolff would later introduce Louise Brooks, star of Pabst's Pandora's Box(1929).(2)
In 1928 Wolff joined Hom Film/Hom-AG für Filmfabrikation as “press and propaganda chief,” “writing press releases, taking newspaper people out to the production sites, placing photographs in papers and in general trying to make a splash where it was possible to make one."(3) While at Hom Film Wolff worked on such Pabst productions as The White Hell of Piz Palue and Diary of a Lost Girl(both 1929), while also doing publicity for Brooks,Luis Trenker, Czech actress Anny Ondra and her then-husband, the Czech director Karel Lamač. After Hom Film disbanded in 1930 Wolff was hired by Ondra-Lamač Film, a production company formed by Ondra and Lamač. Though initially engaged as a publicist on Lamač's Die Vom Rummelplatz/Fair People/Those of the Sideshow(1930), Wolff also served as both assistant director and assistant editor on the production. The following year Wolff continued to work as an assistant director/assistant editor, this time on Lamač's Mamsell Nitouche(1931) produced at the Braunberger-Richebé Studios in Paris. When Lamač later departed for Prague soon after initial production on Der Falsche Feldmarschall/Monsieur le Maréchal(1931) was complete, Wolff was left to edit the film on his own. Before leaving Ondra-Lamač Film in 1931, Wolff worked primarily as assistant director on three additional Lamač films:Eine Freundin So Goldig Wei Du(1930),Er und Seine Schwester/Meet the Sister and Der Zinker/The Squeeker(both 1931).
In 1931 Wolff was hired as chief film editor for Société de Films Osso/Les Films Osso, a Paris-based production company specializing in foreign productions. After editing Osso's Le Costaud des PTT(1931, d. Jean Bertin) and Le Parfum de la Dame en Noir(1931, d. Marcel L'Herbier), Wolff reluctantly agreed to travel to Nice to edit Baroud(1932) -- released the following year in English as Love in Morocco-- for U.S. director Rex Ingram. After finishing Baroud in Paris and London, Wolff traveled to Budapest to edit several Hungarian productions for Films Osso. In addition to Rouletabille Aviateur/Flying Gold(1932, d. István Székely/Steve Sekely), Wolff edited the French, German and (possibly) Romanian versions of Hungarian director Paul Fejos'Tavaszi Zápor/Spring Rain(1932), retitled Marie, Légend Hongroise in France;Marie/Frühlingsregen Oder Marie -- Ein Ungarische Legende in Germany; and Prima Dragoste in Romania.(4) While in Hungary Wolff edited a second film for Fejos,Itél a Balaton/Tempétes/Menschen im Sturm (1933).
Temporarily returning to Berlin in late 1932, Wolff agreed to edit the shorter French version of Fritz Lang's The Testament of Dr. Mabuse.Le Testament du Dr. Mabuse(1933) was adapted from Lang's original script by René Sti and featured a mostly French supporting cast. Anticipating a Nazi ban on the film, Wolff, Sti and Mr. Trevor, Lang's English producer, successfully smuggled a print of the film out of Germany aboard a Paris-bound train. Wolff finished editing Dr. Mabuse in Paris in early 1933 but would not return to Germany until after the war. Later that same year Wolff accompanied Fejos to Vienna for the production of two films --Sonnenstrahl/Gardez le Sourire/Ray of Sunshine and Frühlingsstimmen(both 1933) -- after which Wolff returned to Paris to edit Poliche(1934) for director Abel Gance. In 1934 Wolff traveled to Denmark where he worked as assistant director and editor on three more Fejos productions --Flugten Fra Millionerne/Flight from the Millions/Millions in Flight(1934),Det Gyldne Smil/The Golden Smile, and Fange Nr. 1(both 1935). The following year Wolff edited Fredløs for the Danish director George Schnéevoigt. In January 1936 Wolff immigrated to the United States, possibly aboard the S.S. Scanmail.
Though he originally planned to continue on to Hollywood, Wolff instead settled in New York City where, through the actress Margaret Mullen, he was introduced to Louis de Rochemont, co-creator and producer of Time, Inc.'s monthly theatrical newsreel series The March of Time(Mullen had appeared in a number of the series' dramatic recreations). A few weeks after their initial meeting De Rochemont hired Wolff as a film cutter at The March of Time for a two-month trial period at a salary of $25 per week. (Although occasionally used synonymously, in film-production parlance "cutter" and "editor" refer to two distinct jobs. A cutter is responsible for the mechanical cutting and splicing of film footage based on the creative decisions made by the editor. Wolff arrived at Time, Inc. with considerable experience as an editor, but needed to be taught the basics of film splicing in order to fulfill his new -- and lower -- position as a cutter. In Europe the cutting had always been done by Wolff's assistants.[5]) At the end of the trial period de Rochemont renewed Wolff's contract and doubled his salary. Soon after Wolff was promoted to Chief Editor.
In 1940, one year before the United States' entry into World War II, Wolff edited The March of Time's first feature film The Ramparts We Watch(1940), a docudrama set in a small American town in the years immediately preceding U.S. intervention in World War I.The Ramparts We Watch was produced and directed by de Rochemont and distributed theatrically by RKO. Wolff also edited The Story of the Vatican(1941) and served as associate director on We Are the Marines(1942), two March of Time features distributed by RKO and Twentieth Century Fox, respectively.
Although March of Time staff were exempt from service, in 1944 Wolff went on military leave from Time, Inc. after receiving a commission from the U.S. Coast Guard to serve as Officer-in-Charge (Lt. Commander) of the Film Section of Public Information. Under Wolff's direction, the film unit produced public information films, a monthly screen magazine and several documentaries about the Coast Guard's wartime activities, including Normandy Invasion(1944). Some, like Beachhead to Berlin(1944), were theatrically distributed by Warner Bros.
After receiving an honorable discharge in May 1946, Wolff returned to The March of Time where he worked as an associate producer on three subjects: “Is Everybody Listening?”, “Storm over Britain”, and “End of an Empire?" about Indonesia's struggle for independence. The same year Wolff married Denver, Colorado, native Violet M. Macy(b. 1928), aka "Vee." In late 1949 de Rochemont, who had left The March of Time in 1943, invited Wolff to join the recently formed Louis de Rochemont Associates production company in New York City. Wolff was appointed vice-president and served as an associate producer on The Earth and Its Peoples(1947-48), a series of 36 youth-oriented "human geography" films of which "Nomads of the Jungle" (1947) was the first. In 1949 Wolff was the associate producer of the Reader's Digest-de Rochemont (RD-DR) co-production Lost Boundaries, a feature-length drama about racial prejudice.
Taking a leave of absence from Louis de Rochemont Associates later in 1949, Wolff served as Chief of the Motion Picture Section of the Economic Cooperation Administration (ECA) Information Office under Information Division Director Roscoe Drummond.(6) (The ECA administered the European Recovery Program, commonly known as the Marshall Plan.) Wolff relocated to Paris where, under the auspices of the ECA, he supervised the production of an estimated 50 European documentaries. According to Wolff the purpose of these films was to "subtly publicize the contribution of the Marshall Plan to Europe's economy," and "show the still shell-shocked Europeans that the future was looking brighter and, very important, to promote inter-European unity and cooperation".(7) After 18 months in Paris Wolff returned to New York City and Louis de Rochemont Associates, where he served as associate producer on the dramatic features The Whistle at Eaton Falls(1951) and Walk East on Beacon!(1952). In 1953 Wolff co-wrote and produced the biographical drama Martin Luther, his first feature as producer. Produced by Lutheran Film Associates, a religious production and distribution agency for which Wolff would later produce the feature films Question 7 and The Joy of Bach,Martin Luther was nominated for two Academy Awards: Best Cinematography and Best Art Direction-Set Decoration (Black-and-White).
Later in 1953 Wolff moved to Djakarta, Indonesia, where he was director of a motion-picture technical assistance team assigned to the Indonesian Government Film Studio (P.F.N.) by the A.I.D.(8) Wolff remained in Djakarta until 1955.
On October 28, 1957, Wolff appeared alongside Frank Capra on a Museum of Modern Art"Prospects for the Film" panel entitled "The Propaganda and the Journalistic Film." In 1958 Wolff once again worked as associate producer for Louis de Rochemont Associates on the feature-length documentary Windjammer: The Voyage of the Christian Radich, the first and only film presented in widescreen "Cinemiracle," a would-be competitor to Cinerama. The following year Wolff served as associate producer on the de Rochemont production Man on a String(1960). In 1960 Wolff also independently produced Planet Earth, a series of 13 half-hour, introductory level educational films about geophysical science for the National Academy of Sciences, a project initiated as part of the International Geophysical Year of 1957-58. (Planet Earth was broadcast on television, then distributed to schools on 16mm film by McGraw-Hill.) During this time Wolff directed three segments of the WGBH-TV French-language instruction television series Parlons Français, produced by Heath-de Rochemont & Co. In 1961 Wolff produced the feature film Question 7 for RD-DR and served as associate producer alongside producer Louis de Rochemont on the Warner Bros. feature The Roman Spring of Mrs. Stone starring Vivien Leigh and Warren Beatty.
After producing The Challenge of Change: A Case for Counseling(1962), an educational film about high-school guidance counseling for Louis de Rochemont Associates, Wolff established Lothar Wolff Productions in New York City in 1963 (the company was dissolved in 1966). The same year, Wolff produced Vigilant Switzerland for the Swiss Federal Department of Defense. Originally exhibited as a 70mm multi-screen cinematic experience in the Swiss Army Pavilion at the 1964 Swiss national exhibition (Expo64) in Lausanne,Vigilant Switzerland was later distributed by Cinerama as Fortress of Peace(1965), under which title it received an Academy Award nomination for Best Short Subject (Live Action) in 1966.
In 1966 Wolff also produced the series The Sun and the Earth for the National Academy of Sciences commemorating the Year of the Quiet Sun (1964-65). The number of half-hour episodes produced is uncertain; the 1967-68 National Academy of Sciences Annual Report mentions that four of seven planned films had been produced; Wolff's CV located in Box C310 states he produced a total of five half-hour films. The films were shown on WNET television and distributed by McGraw-Hill. The following year Wolff directed the Louis de Rochemont Associates production Her Name Was Ellie, His Name Was Lyle(1967), a public service film about venereal disease sponsored by the New York City Department of Health.
From 1968 to 1971 Wolff served as executive producer of the Time-Life Films series Life Around Us. Originally titled The World We Live In, the series was later renamed for 16mm non-theatrical use and, possibly, the original television broadcast of Season 2. Consisting of 26 half-hour programs (Season 1 comprised 14 episodes; Season 2 comprised 12), the series was first aired on PBS and later syndicated for broadcast both in the US and abroad.Life Around Us/The World We Live In segments were all original productions. "Rock-a-Bye Baby" (1970), a segment about early human development, won the Emily Award for best film at the American Film Festival. In March 1971 it was screened along with nine additional series segments as a part of a weekly hour-long program at the Museum of Modern Art.
Beginning in 1973 Wolff executive produced two additional series for Time-Life Films.Wild, Wild World of Animals(1973-74) consisted of 26 half-hour documentary programs narrated by William Conrad and was syndicated throughout the US.Other People, Other Places(1973-75), a series of previously produced ethnographic documentaries that had been adapted into 52 half-hour television episodes, was sponsored by Miles Laboratories and hosted by actor Peter Graves. Syndicated throughout the US,Other People, Other Places was retitled Strange Places in the New York City area to avoid confusion with a similarly titled series airing in the same timeslot.
From October 1, 1975, through 1977 Wolff served as consultant to the Educational Film Section of the National Geographic Society. Among Wolff's chief duties was stockpiling "completed productions from various producers" for "possible later TV syndication."(9) As he had with Other People, Other Places, Wolff would then adapt these predominantly ethnographic films for U.S. broadcast.(10) In 1976 Wolff produced The March of Time, a 30-minute film for North German Television about the origins and influence of the newsreel series. That same year Wolff served as the editorial director of I Sought My Brother, aka I Shall Moulder Before I Shall Be Taken, a one-hour documentary about the Maroons, or "Bush Negroes," of Surinam produced by Harvard University. During 1977 Wolff was also employed as a consultant by Metropolitan Pittsburgh Public Broadcasting (WQED).
In 1977 Wolff began production on a long-planned biographical film about Johann Sebastian Bach. First televised on PBS on December 23, 1979,The Joy of Bach featured musical recitals as well as dramatic recreations starring actor Brian Blessed as Bach. In November 1978 Wolff traveled to Switzerland to introduce a March of Time retrospective at the 10th International Documentary Film Festival in Nyon. Running approximately 14 hours, this multi-session program showed all March of Time shorts made between 1935 and 1937. In November 1979 Wolff attended the Yorkton International Film Festival in Saskatchewan, Canada, where he introduced "The History of March of Time" sessions and conducted a seminar on the making of The Joy of Bach entitled "The Total Picture of Making a Film." The following month he introduced a week-long March of Time retrospective at the XX Festival dei Popoli in Florence, Italy.
From 1979-81 Wolff produced a series of three films for the National Geographic Society Educational Film Section:The Moon[aka Reflecting the Moon],The Sun[aka The Sun: The Earth's Star] and The Solar System. Much of the filming was done at the Kitt Peak National Observatory in Tuscon, Arizona. In 1980 Wolff was also hired by Beta/Taurus Films, GmbH to serve as a consultant on a planned production of 32 one-hour films based on the Old Testament titled Fernsehbibel/The TV Bible. The following year Wolff began work on Planet Earth Revisited, a planned sequel to the TV series Planet Earth commemorating the 25th anniversary of the International Geophysical Year (IGY). The series was eventually produced by WQED under the title Planet Earth, but without Wolff's involvement. In 1981 Wolff also received an honorary degree from Thiel College in Greenville, PA.
In 1983 Wolff produced A Parade of Witnesses, a one-hour live television program for Satellite Broadcasting commemorating the 500th anniversary of the birth of Martin Luther. The following year Wolff produced and directed Sky's the Limit(working title From Montgolfier to Satellite), a one-hour documentary commemorating the bicentennial of the first public hot-air balloon demonstration by the Montgolfier brothers in 1783. In 1984 Wolff attended a March of Time retrospective in Tokyo.
On October 2, 1988, Lothar Wolff died of prostate cancer at Rosary Hill Home nursing facility in Hawthorne, NY. At the time of his death Wolff had been living with his wife, Violet, in Sharon, Connecticut.
1. Jan-Christopher Horak, "Rin-Tin-Tin in Berlin, or American Cinema in Weimar,"Film History, Volume 5 (1993), 49-62.
2. Lothar Wolff, "Reminiscences of an Itinerant Filmmaker,"Journal of the University Film Association, Vol. 24, No. 4 (1972), 83-91.
3. Lothar Wolff interview, Box C301, folder 60.
4. According to the website Secvenţe: Film Româneşti [http://secvente.ro/2012/06/prima-dragoste-marie/] eight versions of Marie were shot in Budapest in 1933. Each starred the French actress Annabella but each version often featured a different supporting cast.
5. Raymond Fielding,The March of Time, 1935-1951(New York: Oxford University Press, 1978), 112.
6. Regina M. Longo, "Between Documentary and Neorealism: Marshall Plan Films in Italy (1948-1955)."California Italian Studies 3:2 (2012): 17-19.
7. Wolff, "Reminiscences of an Itinerant Filmmaker," 83-91.
8. In a CV found in box C310 Wolff refers to this agency as "A.I.D.", an acronym for the Agency for International Development. Considering the A.I.D. was not founded until 1961, Wolff may be referring to a precursor organization.
9. December 16, 1975, letter to Lester Wunderman from Sidney Platt, Supervisor Educational Film Projects, National Geographic Society. Box C355, Folder 35.
10. December 20, 1975, letter to Hugh Gibb. Box C355, Folder 32.
Scope and Content Note
The Lothar Wolff Collection consists of correspondence (both business and personal), photographs, publications and clippings, research materials, awards and citations, artwork, and film and video dating from 1926 to 1987. The bulk of the collection represents Wolff’s professional career, including materials related to completed and proposed film and television projects and other business dealings; very little is of a personal nature. The collection includes material documenting Wolff’s involvement with many notable figures involved in motion pictures, including Louis de Rochemont, Louise Brooks, G. W. Pabst, and Paul Fejos.
Wolff maintained fairly well-organized files on most of the projects he was involved in, including many that were never produced. These materials cover his work in pre-World War II Europe, his time as editor for The March of Time newsreel series, and his work as an independent producer. It includes his collaborations with the Lutheran Film Associates and the National Geographic Society. Geographically, the majority of the collection was produced in the United States, but a portion of it originated in Europe. The timeline of the collection covers the majority of Wolff’s career, with no significant gaps.
The collection also includes several items that have unclear provenance, and their connection to Wolff is unknown. These items include Czech animation cells and British Film Institute (BFI)Monthly Film Bulletins.
Arrangement of the Collection
Papers are arranged in 10 series according to subject, and in the case of artworks, artifacts, photographs, and film, according to format. The series "Business Materials" has been further subdivided into subseries, and "Film/TV Projects" into subseries and sub-subseries according to film series title and episode name. Paper materials are largely arranged in reverse chronological order as found. Most photographs appear to have been previously arranged into albums according subject and/or time period, some further arranged in chronological order. Additional photographs can be found along with related materials in their folders. Artwork and artifacts are grouped according to size. Films and video are located in the film vaults at the George Eastman Museum and are arranged according to the Moving Image Department's location protocols. The series and subseries arrangement of the records are as follows:
Series 1, Business Materials,1933-1985
Subseries 1,Time, Inc./Time-Life,1968-1981
Subseries 2,Lutheran Film Associates,1978-1983
Subseries 3, General,1947-1985
Series 2, Film/TV Projects,1932-1986
Subseries 1,Earth and Its Peoples,ca. 1932,1938,1951-1962,1967-1986
Subseries 2,Fortress of Peace[aka Vigilant Switzerland],1964-1966
Subseries 3,The Joy of Bach,1967-1985,bulk 1977-1980
Subseries 4,Lost Boundaries,1949
Subseries 5,The March of Time,1933,1936-1951,1957,1969-1970,1979-1982
Subseries 6, Marshall Plan Films,1951,1979
Subseries 7,Martin Luther,1952-1954,1971,1978,1983
Subseries 8, National Geographic Society Films [General],1973-1983
Subseries 9,Other People, Other Places,1971-1975,1980
Subseries 10,A Parade of Witnesses,1953,1979-1983
Subseries 11,Planet Earth/Planet Earth Revisited,1960-1963,1979-1983
Subseries 12,Question 7,1961-1962
Subseries 13,The Roman Spring of Mrs. Stone,1961,1979
Subseries 14,Sky's the Limit,1969-1985
Subseries 15,The Sun/The Moon/The Solar System,1971-1985,undated